Guide to the Dachine Rainer Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Dachine Rainer papers
1913-2000
YCAL MSS 639
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
36.59
(42 boxes)
The collection documents the life and work of poet and author Dachine Rainer (pseudonym of Sylvia Newman) and her relationships with other literary figures, particularly Rebecca West. Material includes correspondence, writings, personal papers, photographs, printed material, and a computer disk.
Rainer, Dachine
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Bernard Quaritch Ltd. on the Eugene G. O'Neill Memorial Fund, 2001.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 41 (computer disk): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Box 42 (correspondence): Restricted until 2060. For further information consult appropriate curator.
Dachine Rainer (1921-2000)
Dachine Rainer, American-born poet, author, and anarchist. Rainer was born Sylvia Newman in New York on January 13, 1921, and studied English literature at Hunter College. Her published works include: poems, essays, and articles in periodicals such as The New Republic and The Nation; and the books The Uncomfortable Inn (1960) and Giornale de Venezia (1996). Rainer befriended Rebecca West after moving to London in 1961. She died on August 19, 2000 and is buried in Highgate Cemetery.
Scope and Contents
The collection documents the life and work of poet and author Dachine Rainer (pseudonym of Sylvia Newman) and her relationships with other literary figures, particularly Rebecca West. Material includes correspondence, writings, personal papers, photographs, printed material, and a computer disk.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Correspondence, 1930-2000. II. Rebecca West Material, 1913-1996. III. Writings, 1936-1996. IV. Personal and Other Papers, 1938-2000.
American literature -- 20th Century; American poetry -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Poets, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Born digital; Photographs; Authors; Poets; Rainer, Dachine; West, Rebecca, 1892-1983
- Correspondence, 1930-2000; Series I; 9; (9 boxes)
  - "A" general, 1955-1981 (Box 1)
  - Agenda, 1986-1997; 2 (Box 1)
  - Artwatch, 2000 (Box 1)
  - Auden, W. H., 1941-1973 (Box 1)
  - Avrich, Paul, 1977, 1988 (Box 1)
  - "B" general, 1959-1985 (Box 1)
  - Babel, Isaac, related correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - Balcomb, John, 1970-1993 (Box 1)
  - Ballantine, Edward J., 1963-1983; 3 (Box 1)
  - Barrer, Gertrude, 1948-1949 (Box 1)
  - Bayley, John, 1994-1996 (Box 1)
  - Bellow, Saul, 1942 (Box 1)
  - Berryman, John, undated (Box 1)
  - Bernelle, Agnes, 1980-1989 (Box 1)
  - Bogan, Louise, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Brokenshaw, Louise, 1966-1979 (Box 1)
  - Burke, Jackson, 1953-1954 (Box 1)
  - "C" general, 1962-1973 (Box 1)
  - Cantine, Therese (Rainer's daughter), 1953-1996; 13 (Box 2)
  - Chomsky, Noam, 1996 September 23 (Box 2)
  - Chwast, Seymour, 1947-1993; 2 (Box 2)
  - Comfort, Alex, 1983-1996 (Box 2)
  - "D-E" general, 1941-1963 (Box 2)
  - "F" general, 1943-1985; 2 (Box 3)
  - "G" general, 1958-1970 (Box 3)
  - "H" general, 1942-1990 (Box 3)
  - Hennacy, Ammon, 1942-1948 (Box 3)
  - Huxley, Aldous, 1938 (Box 3)
  - Isherwood, Christopher, 1949-1977 (Box 3)
  - "J" general, 1948-1979 (Box 3)
  - "K" general, 1948-1961 (Box 3)
  - Krim, Seymour, 1956-1970 (Box 3)
  - "L" general, 1951-1993 (Box 3)
  - Levertov, Denise, 1960-1961 (Box 3)
  - "M" general, 1930-1984 (Box 3)
  - MacDonald, Nancy and Dwight, 1960-1983; 2 (Box 3)
  - Mailer, Norman, 1955-1992 (Box 3)
  - Murdoch, Iris, 1967 (Box 3)
  - "N-O", 1967-1981 (Box 3)
  - New Directions, 1950-1990 (Box 3)
  - Newman, Esther (Rainer's mother), 1945-1973; 4 (Box 3)
  - Newman, Carl (Rainer's brother), 1962-1995; 2 (Box 3)
  - Newman family, 1967-1999 (Box 4)
  - "P" general, 1942-1993 (Box 4)
  - Pacifism, 1960 (Box 4)
  - Patchen, Kenneth, 1942-1945 (Box 4)
  - The Pushpin Group and miscellaneous, 1980-1990 (Box 4)
  - "R" general, 1946-1966 (Box 4)
  - Rachewiltz, Mary de, 1983-1991 (Box 4)
  - Raine, Kathleen, 1994-1996 (Box 4)
  - Retort, 1943-1948; 11 (Box 4)
  - Rexroth, Kenneth, 1941-1969 (Box 4)
  - Russell, Bertrand, 1960-1961 (Box 4)
  - Russell, Peter, 1972 (Box 4)
  - "S" general, 1941-1975; 2 (Box 5)
  - Salzburg, University of, 1995-1998 (Box 5)
  - Shirley, George, 1969-1989 (Box 5)
  - Sistine Chapel Restoration, correspondence about, 1992 (Box 5)
  - Spectator, 1996-1998 (Box 5)
  - "T-U" general, 1945-1973 (Box 5)
  - "W" general, 1948-1981 (Box 5)
  - Walter, Nicholas, 1988 February-April (Box 5)
  - West, Kitty, 1964-1999 (Box 5)
  - Woodcock, George, 1946-1995 (Box 5)
  - Yale, 1996-1998 (Box 5)
  - Cards. Seasonal, birthday and travel, undated; 12 (Box 5)
  - Cards. Seasonal, birthday and travel, undated; 19 (Box 6)
  - Sympathy cards (Teddy's death), 1968 (Box 6)
  - Unsorted literary correspondence, undated; 6 (Box 6)
  - Unsorted literary correspondence, undated; 19 (Box 7)
  - Unsorted literary correspondence, undated; 3 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous unsorted correspondence, 1950-1999; 20 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous unsorted correspondence, 1950-1999; 18 (Box 9)
- Rebecca West Material, 1913-1996; Series II; 1.21; (2 boxes)
  - Dachine Rainer Correspondence
    - West to Rainer, 1962-1982, undated; 5 (Box 10)
    - Andrews, Henry (West's husband), 1962-1968 (Box 10)
    - Rainer to West and Andrews, 1961-1978; 2 (Box 10)
    - Rainer's correspondence regarding Rebecca West to publishers and newspapers, outlines for the Rebecca West Reader, Kitty West, Hetty Muirhead, 1960-1973 (Box 10)
  - Writings
    - "In Search of Rebecca West's Harry," copy of typescript, 1967 (Box 10)
    - "This Happens Down Our Way All the Time", 1968 (Box 10)
      Scope and Contents
      Typescript poem by West with revisions. Photocopy of the title page from "Oh Heaven and Poems Written On Active Service" by Ford Hueffer with inscriptions.
    - Rainer's notes on West, 1960-1970 (Box 10)
    - "Dame Rebecca West-Disturber of the Peace," typescript, corrected, 1965 (Box 10)
    - "No Thanks," excerpts regarding West, 1975 (Box 10)
    - Articles on Rebecca West by Rainer that appeared in The New Republic, Manchester Guardian, Commonwealth, Spectator, and Sunday Telegram, printed versions, 1957-1971 (Box 10)
    - Drafts and corrected manuscripts on West by Rainer, undated (Box 10)
    - Reviews and articles written by Rebecca West, clippings, 1913-1980 (Box 10)
    - Reviews and interviews of Rebecca West, clippings, 1946-1979 (Box 10)
    - West ephemera, 1982-1986; 4 (Box 10)
      Includes newspaper clippings, notes, articles and the order of service for West's funeral at St.Martin-in-the-Field
    - Photographs, undated; 7 (Box 11)
- Writings, 1936-1996; Series III; 16.25; (18 boxes)
  - "The Fragile Idyll" (also called "L'Escargot"), original manuscript, photocopies with corrections, carbons, typescripts, drafts, notes, correspondence, and related material, 1950-1980; 13 (Box 12)
  - "The Fragile Idyll" (continued), 1950-1980; 9 (Box 13)
  - "In Search of Rebecca West's Harry," autograph manuscript and copy, 1967; 2 (Box 13)
  - "For The Three Of Us," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 13)
  - "No Thanks," typescripts, photocopies, notes, related material, and correspondence, 1975; 11 (Box 14)
  - "No Thanks", 1975; 5; Includes 1 computer disk. (Box 15)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Computer disks are restricted. Copies of electronic files may be requested through Access Services: Disk #2001.ycal.0313-g, "BOOK.DOC. PART2.DOC. PART3.DOC"
  - "Copper Colored," typescript copies, some corrected, photocopies, notes, and related material, 1979; 17 (Box 16)
  - "Adam and Eve," autograph manuscript notes, typescript introduction, layout, photographs, and illustrations, 1975; 6 (Box 17)
  - "Rembrandt," manuscript, typescripts of various drafts, correspondence, notes, and other material, 1972-1975; 10 (Box 17)
  - "The Uncomfortable Inn," edited manuscript, typescript numerous copies, reviews, related correspondence, and notes, 1960; 11 (Box 18)
  - "The Uncomfortable Inn" (continued), 1960; 4 (Box 19)
  - "Cousins: The Will of Marion Harbord," typescript, manuscript, numerous photocopies, some corrected, notes, and related material, 1993; 12 (Box 20)
  - "Cousins: The Will of Marion Harbord" (continued), 1993; 6 (Box 21)
  - "The Will of Mitt," final typescript, pages 1-50 missing, undated; 2 (Box 21)
  - "For The Three of Us", undated (Box 21)
  - "Outside Time," manuscript, corrected and typescript (copies), 1939 (Box 21)
  - "Giornale di Venezia," galleys, notes, corrected manuscript, reviews, and correspondence, 1996; 2 (Box 21)
  - "Giornale di Venezia" (continued), 1996; 7 (Box 22)
  - "Famous Americans," typescript, undated (Box 22)
  - Censorship, 1985 (Box 22)
  - "Tom Keating and the Art Establishment," manuscript, corrected, clippings, notes, photographs, and correspondence, 1976; 2 (Box 22)
  - "Ballet," manuscript, corrected, notes, photographs, and correspondence, 1970 (Box 22)
  - Anti-War, manuscript, clippings, notes, and correspondence, 1991; 2 (Box 22)
  - Selected Poems, typescripts, notes, and correspondence, 1961-1987; 12 (Box 23)
  - "Ripeness Is All," manuscript, photocopies, and notes, 1936-1969 (Box 23)
  - The Early Poems, handwritten and typed poetry with related correspondence, 1940-1960; 3 (Box 23)
  - "Premonition of Bedlam," working copy, 1939; 2 (Box 24)
  - "Loves Delights and Lamentations," edited typescript and photocopies, undated (Box 24)
  - "Cambridge and Vienna," manuscript, with other writings, 1966 (Box 24)
  - "Anarchism: Recent Thoughts," manuscript, notes and correspondence, 1972 (Box 24)
  - "Double Agent," manuscript, newspapers and corrected typescript, 1955 (Box 24)
  - "Borneo," manuscript and notes, 1970 (Box 24)
  - "Conversations With My Dog," manuscript, edited typescript and notes, undated (Box 24)
  - "Lost," typescripts, corrected, undated; 3 (Box 24)
  - Reviews, 1952-1980 (Box 24)
    Includes published reviews by Rainer that appeared in various magazines and correspondence with editors
  - "The Story Of An Infatuation," typescript, carbon copy, undated (Box 24)
  - "The Cat Door," typescript, corrected, notes, undated (Box 24)
  - E. E. Cummings, notes, writings, correspondence, and related material about the poet, 1955-1962; 6 (Box 25)
  - Balcomb, manuscript, corrected (copy), 1986 (Box 25)
  - The Artist Bonnington, notes, letters, rewrites, and synopsis, 1978 (Box 25)
  - "Ezra Pound: Reminiscences and Opinions," typescripts, manuscript, related material, correspondence, notes and clippings, 1986-1992; 6 (Box 25)
  - "Ezra Pound: Reminiscences and Opinions" (continued), 1986-1992; 17 (Box 26)
  - Periodicals featuring Rainer's work
    - Anarchy, 1962-1968 (Box 27)
    - Commonwealth, 1964-1968 (Box 27)
    - Liberation, 1961-1964 (Box 27)
    - Listener, 1967 (Box 27)
    - Nation, 1956-1961 (Box 27)
    - New Republic, 1955-1970 (Box 27)
    - New Statesman, 1980 (Box 27)
    - The Match, 1987 (Box 27)
    - Francis Routh, undated (Box 27)
    - The Spectator, 1990-1995 (Box 27)
    - Syracuse, 1961 (Box 27)
    - The Wasp, 1952-1954 (Box 27)
  - Unsorted writings by Rainer and others
    - Poems, short stories, notes, and related material, 1950-1996; 16 (Box 28)
    - Poems, short stories, notes, and related material, 1950-1996; 17 (Box 29)
- Personal and Other Papers, 1938-2000; Series IV; 8.83; (10 boxes) (Box 29)
  - Diaries and Address Books
    - Diaries, 1961-1979; 17 (Box 30)
    - Diaries, 1980-1994; 16 (Box 31)
    - Diaries, 1995-2000; 8 (Box 32)
    - Address books, notebook, undated; 5 (Box 32)
  - Student Papers
    - Morris High School Yearbook, 1938 (Box 33)
    - Hunter College essays and school papers, 1938-1941; 2 (Box 33)
    - Hunter College diploma, 1941 (Box 33)
  - Dwelley Farm, 1978-1984; 20 (Box 34)
    Includes letters to police, private investigators, British Parliament, local government agencies, newspapers, tradesmen, utility companies and chemical laboratories.
  - Dwelley Farm (continued), 1978-1984; 20 (Box 35)
  - Dwelley Farm (continued), 1978-1984; 21 (Box 36)
  - Dwelley Farm (continued), 1978-1984; 7 (Box 37)
  - Real estate papers, undated (Box 38)
  - Legal papers, undated (Box 38)
  - Medical papers, 1950-1999; 13 (Box 38)
  - Passports and government-issues documents, 1967-1997 (Box 38)
  - Spiral notebooks, undated; 3 (Box 39)
  - Unsorted material, correspondence, typescripts, notes, and clippings, 1954-1971; 3 (Box 39)
  - Unsorted material, correspondence, typescripts, notes, and clippings, undated; 13 (Box 39)
  - Financial papers, undated (Box 39)
- Oversize, 0.08; (1 box)
  - Photographs (from Series II), undated; 2 (Box 40 (Oversize))
  - "Adam and Eve," photographs (from Series III) (Box 40 (Oversize))
- Computer media, 0.21; (1 box)
  - "No Thanks" (from Series III), (1 computer disk)
    - Formatted 25.10.89 MICROSOFT WORD 5.0 BOOK.DOC PART2.DOC PART3.DOC, 2001-ycal-0313-g-0001; 1 (Box 41)
      Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
- Restricted, 1; (1 box)
  - Correspondence (restricted until 2060) (Box 42)
    Restricted until 2060. For further information consult appropriate curator.